<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Ian Bicking: a blog</title><link href="http://www.ianbicking.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.ianbicking.org/feeds/mozila.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.ianbicking.org/</id><updated>2019-03-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Open Source Doesn’t Make Money Because It Isn’t Designed To Make Money</title><link href="http://www.ianbicking.org/blog/2019/03/open-source-doesnt-make-money-by-design.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2019-03-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Ian Bicking</name></author><id>tag:www.ianbicking.org,2019-03-18:blog/2019/03/open-source-doesnt-make-money-by-design.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or: &lt;em&gt;The Best Way To Do Something Is To At Least&amp;nbsp;Try&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all know the story: you can&amp;#8217;t make money on open source. Is it really&amp;nbsp;true?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m thinking about this now because Mozilla would like to diversify its revenue in the next few years, and one constraint we have is that everything we do is open&amp;nbsp;source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are dozens (hundreds?) of successful open source projects that have tried to become even just modest commercial enterprises, some very seriously. Results aren&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I myself am trying to pitch a commercial endeavor in Mozilla right now (if writing up plans and sending them into the ether can qualify as &amp;#8220;pitching&amp;#8221;), and this question often comes up in feedback: can we sell something that is open&amp;nbsp;source?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no evidence that we can (or can&amp;#8217;t), but I will make this assertion: it&amp;#8217;s hard to sell something that wasn&amp;#8217;t designed to be&amp;nbsp;sold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We treat open source like it&amp;#8217;s a poison pill for a commercial product. And yes, with an open source license it&amp;#8217;s harder to force someone to pay for a product, though many successful businesses exist without &lt;em&gt;forcing&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see an implicit assumption that makes it harder to think about this: the idea that if something is useful, it should be profitable. It&amp;#8217;s an unspoken and morally-infused expectation, a kind of Just World hypothesis: if something has utility, if it helps people, if it&amp;#8217;s something the world needs, if it empowers other people, then there should be a revenue opportunity. It should be possible for the thing to be your day job, to make money, to see some renumeration for your successful effort in creating or doing this&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s what we think the world &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be like, but we all know it isn&amp;#8217;t. You can&amp;#8217;t make a living making music. Or art. You can&amp;#8217;t even make a living taking care of children. I think this underlies many of this moment&amp;#8217;s critiques of capitalism: there&amp;#8217;s too many things that are important, even needed, or that fulfill us more than any profitable item, and yet are economically&amp;nbsp;unsustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;#8217;t try to fix that in this blog post, but let us just recall that it is there: not all good things make&amp;nbsp;money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, we know there is money in software. Lots of money! Is the money in secrets? If OpenSSL was secret, could it make money? If it had a licensing paywall, could it make money? Seems unlikely. The license isn&amp;#8217;t holding it back. It&amp;#8217;s just not shaped like something that makes money. Solving important problems isn&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what can you get paid to&amp;nbsp;do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People will pay a little for apps; not a lot, but a bit. Scaling up requires marketing and capital, which open source projects almost never have (and I doubt many open source projects would know what to do with capital if they had&amp;nbsp;it).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&amp;#8217;s always money in ads. Sadly. This could potentially offend someone enough to actually repackage your open source software with ads removed. As a form of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price_discrimination"&gt;price discrimination&lt;/a&gt; (e.g., paid ad removal) it can still be&amp;nbsp;successful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fully-hosted services: &lt;a href="https://automattic.com/"&gt;Automattic&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; wordpress.com is a good example here. Is &lt;a href="https://ghost.org/"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt; doing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People will pay if you ensure they get a personalized solution. In other words: consulting. Applied to software you get &lt;a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2002/05/06/five-worlds/"&gt;consultingware&lt;/a&gt;. While often maligned, many real businesses are built on this. I think Drupal is in this&amp;nbsp;category.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People will pay you for your dedicated and ongoing attention. In other words: a day job as an employee. It feels unfair to put this option on the list, but it&amp;#8217;s such a natural progression from consultingware, and such a dominant pattern in open source that I think it deserves&amp;nbsp;acknowledgement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything paired with a physical device. People will judge the value based on the hardware and software experience&amp;nbsp;together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;m not sure if Firefox makes money (indirectly) from ads, or from maintaining monopoly&amp;nbsp;positions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m sure I&amp;#8217;m missing some interesting ideas from that&amp;nbsp;list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you have a business concept, and you think it might work, what does open source even have to do with it? Don&amp;#8217;t we learn: focus on your business! On your customer! Software licensing seems like a distraction, even &lt;em&gt;software&lt;/em&gt; is a questionable thing to focus on, separate from the business. Maybe this is why you can&amp;#8217;t make money with open source: it&amp;#8217;s a distraction. The question isn&amp;#8217;t open-source-vs-proprietary, but&amp;nbsp;open-source-vs-business-focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another lens might be: who are you selling to? Classical scratch-your-own-itch open source software is built by programmers &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; programmers. And it is wildly successful, but it&amp;#8217;s selling to people who aren&amp;#8217;t willing to pay. They want to take the software and turn it around into greater personal productivity (which turns out to be a smart move, given the rise in programmer wages). Can we sell open source to other people? Can anyone else &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; anything with source&amp;nbsp;code?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so I remain pessimistic that open source can find commercial success. But also frustrated: so much software is open source &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt; any commercial product. This is where the Free Software mission has faltered despite so many successes: software that people actually touch isn&amp;#8217;t free or open. That&amp;#8217;s a&amp;nbsp;shame.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>